A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Lyle Saunders FA631
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Lyle Saunders
1963-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Saunders, Lyle
Ford Foundation
FA631
2.62 Cubic Feet
The International Division/Population Papers of Lyle Saunders were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982. The papers consist of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. They are divided into two series: Population Files and Correspondence Files. Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Saunders' office.
Biographical / Historical
Lyle Saunders, Ford Foundation Program Officer in the International Division (ID), was a member of the Foundation staff from 1964 until 1975. During this period, he held the following positions:
- January 1975, Program Officer, Population Office and Asia and Pacific, ID
- January 1974, Program Officer, Population Office, ID
- January 1973, Advisor in Program Management seconded to the IBRD - National Family Planning Coordinating Board, Jakarta, ID
- January 1971, Program Advisor, AP, Southeast Asia (Thailand), ID
- May 1968, Program Officer, Population Office, ID
- July 1967, Program Advisor, Population Office (Malaysia), ID
- January 1967, Program Officer, Population Office, ID
- October 1966, Associate Director, Population Program, OD
- February 1964, Program Associate, Population Program, OD
Lyle Saunders was born October 16, 1907. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees in 1938 and 1943 respectively, from the University of New Mexico. He did additional course work at the Universities of Chicago and Texas.
Prior to Saunders' career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
- 1942-1951, University of New Mexico Assistant Professor of Sociology, School of Inter-American Affairs
- 1951-1964, University of Colorado, Associate Professor of Sociology, Associate Professor of the Department of Preventive Medicine, Acting Head of the Department of Preventive Medicine and Public Health, School of Medicine, Director of the Institute of Behaviorial Science
- 1961-1962, Government of India Advisor in Research and Evaluation, Central Health Education Bureau
Following his reitrement from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Saunders served the Foundation as a consultant on population related matters off and on from March 1976 until September 1980. He now resides in Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Scope and Contents
These papers, which consist of two boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports, are concerned with the International Division's Population Program for the years 1963 to 1970.
The papers, which are broad in scope, yet lacking in quantity and depth, include material related to population conferences attended by FF staff, overseas program population files, budget material, and other areas of Foundation family planning involvement, including contraceptive research. The papers are indicative of the role Saunders played within the Population Program.
There is also one box of correspondence that Saunders maintained with FF colleagues, grantee organizations, and other individuals in the population field.
Arrangement
The International Division/Population Papers of Lyle Saunders are divided into two series:
I. Population Files
II. Correspondence Files
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned material. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Population Files, 1963-1970; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Population Files (1963-1970), is the most substanitve. It contains material on the activities of the International Division's Population Program.
  Arrangement
  The files, which maintain the order established by Saunders' office, fall into five categories: Conference Files, which are arranged in reverse chronological order; Overseas Program Interest Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order; Family Planning and Population Program Budget Files, which are both arranged in reverse chronological order; and Grant Proposal Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Political Science in Population Studies, Carolina Population Center Workshop, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C. December 10-11, 1970, 1970 November-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Southeast Asia Ministers' Conference, Kuala Lumpur, October 1970, 1970 July-November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Population Communication Conference, Tehran, June 6-18, 1970, 1969 November-1970 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Second National Seminar on General Consequences of Population Growth, Malaysia, March 1970, 1969 August-1970 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Society for International Development, New Delhi, Nov. 14-17, 1969, 1969 July-August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Villa Serbelloni Conference on Population, October 20-22, 1969, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indian Population Advisors Meeting, Altamont, Milbrook, New York, Sep. 23-24, 1969, 1969 February-September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IPPF Meeting at the Ford Foundation, September 22, 1969, 1969 July-September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research Planning Conference, Budapest, September 18-19, 1969, 1969 August-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Workshop on Contraceptive Specifications, August 11-12, 1969, 1969 July-August (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interregional Workshop on Programmes of Training in the Field of Population, Elsinore, Denmark, June 19-30, 1967, 1967 March-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NICHD Conference on Behavioral Sciences and Family Planning, Bethesda, Maryland, June 7-9, 1967, 1967 March-June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ROCAP Conference, San Jose, Costa Rica, February 6-8, 1967, 1966 December-1967 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Macy Foundation Conference, NY,NY, January 6, 1967, 1967 January-February (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notre Dame Conference on Population, South Bend, Indiana, Dec. 1-3, 1966, 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conference on the Physiology of Human Reproduction, Venice, May, 1966, 1965 October-1966 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Overseas Program Interest, Latin America - General, 1966 May-1967 June (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Brazil, 1966 November-1967 March (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Chile, 1967 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Colombia, 1964 August-1967 May (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Costa Rica, 1966 November-1967 June (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Dominican Republic, 1967 January-March (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Overseas Program Interest - El Salvador, 1966 October-1967 May (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Guatemala, 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Mexico, 1966 November-1967 June (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Peru, 1967 January-April (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Overseas Program Interest - SSE Asia - Malaysia, 1965 January-1968 June (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Indonesia, 1967 May-June (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - SSE Asia/India/Social/Sciences, 1968 April-May (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Family Planning - World Activities, 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Family Planning - USA, 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Contraceptives, 1968 May-September (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Population Program Budget Material, 1965 April-1967 June (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Population Program - Fellowships Available, 1965 November (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Population Program - Staff Discussions, 1966 November-1967 April (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Population Program - Staff Discussions, 1963 November-1966 November (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Grant Proposals: BEMFAM, 1966 December-1967 March (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Grant Proposals: Baltimore Planned Parenthood, 1966 October-1967 January (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grant Proposals: Pan American Federation of Associations of Medical Schools, 1967 March-June (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Grant Proposals: University of Rio de Janeiro, 1966 December-1967 March (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grant Proposals: Urban League, 1967 May (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Correspondence Files, 1964-1970; II
  Series II, Correspondence Files (1964-1970), contains correspondence generated by Mr. Saunders during his years at the Foundation.
  The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - AM - AN, 1964 May-1966 February (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - BE - BR, 1964 April-1966 April (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - CA - CR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - DA - DE, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - ER, 1964 June, 1966 June (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - FE - FR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Freedman, Ronald, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - GA - GR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - HA - HO, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - IN - IR, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - India - Freyman, Nyswander, Dhillon, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - JA - JO, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - KA - KO, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - LE - LO, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - MA - MU, 1964-1965, 1966 May (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mc, 1964 December (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - NI - NY, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Nurses Manual, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - OG - OU, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - PA - PI, 1964, 1965 August (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - QU, 1965 April (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - RA - RU, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - SA - SU, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Samora, Julian, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Sweeney, W.O., 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - TA - TI, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - VI, 1965 February (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - WA - WO, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - ZE, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 71)